-
-=
-= L
-= LU
-= LUO
-= LUO M
-= LUO MA
-= LUO MAD
-= LUO MADE
-= LUO MADE D
-= LUO MADE DV
-= LUO MADE DVD
-= LUO MADE DVD =
-= LUO MADE DVD =-
(Touch your bloodstained hands)
(你們摸摸看，你們染血的雙手)
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
You've soiled me with blood
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
看你把我弄得都是血了…
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
Be still!
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
排個隊動來動去
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
Get out!
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
出去！出去！
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
Who the hell let you in?
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
誰跟你說可以進來的
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
Don't you know
this is the Mehebu hunting ground?
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
你不知道這是我馬赫坡的獵場嗎？
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
I don't care if it's your hunting ground or theirs
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
because everything here
belongs to us Japanese now
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
什麼你的獵場，我的獵場？
全部都是我們日本人的！
I hate the Japanese no less than you do
because everything here
belongs to us Japanese now
全部都是我們日本人的！
我對日本人的仇恨
(Touch your angry forehead)
I hate the Japanese no less than you do
(你們摸摸看，你們悲憤的前額)
我對日本人的仇恨
不會少於你們…
(Touch your angry forehead)
But do you realize that
(你們摸摸看，你們悲憤的前額)
只是你們知道行動之後…
(Touch your angry forehead)
we're going to die after all this
and all our people will be wiped out?
(你們摸摸看，你們悲憤的前額)
我們一定會死…甚至滅族嗎？
(Touch your angry forehead)
Mouna, you must keep the intruders
away from our clan
(你們摸摸看，你們悲憤的前額)
莫那…
千萬不能讓異族人進到部落…
(Touch your angry forehead)
(你們摸摸看，你們悲憤的前額)
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
Inform the chiefs of all the 12 clans
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
聯絡十二個血盟部落的頭目…
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
Tomorrow morning..
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
明天上午…
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
we're going to gather in Wushe
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
一起在霧社集合
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
and offer a blood sacrifice to our ancestors
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
…血祭祖靈！
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
My children! What are you doing?
孩子啊！你們在做什麼？
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
What on earth are you doing, my children?
My children! What are you doing?
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
孩子啊！你們在做什麼？
我的孩子啊，你們在做什麼？
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
(How much pain
do you swallow to sing the ancestral songs?)
(為唱出祖靈的歌需要吞下許多痛苦)
(How much pain
do you swallow to sing the ancestral songs?)
Tanah, why are you doing this?
(為唱出祖靈的歌需要吞下許多痛苦)
達那哈…
你們為什麼要這樣哪？
(How much shame
do you swallow to speak out your minds?)
Tanah, why are you doing this?
(為說出自己的話需要吞下許多屈辱)
你們為什麼要這樣哪？
(How much shame
do you swallow to speak out your minds?)
It was Mouna Rudo's idea
(為說出自己的話需要吞下許多屈辱)
全部都算莫那魯道的…
(How much shame
do you swallow to speak out your minds?)
(為說出自己的話需要吞下許多屈辱)
(How much regret
do you swallow to fulfill your dreams?)
(為實現夢想需要吞下許多遺憾)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(孩子啊，你們怎麼了？)
(Oh, my children!
What exactly is wrong with you?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們到底怎麼了？)
(Your dreams are vast like a blue ocean)
(你們夢廣大如一片藍色海洋)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(孩子啊，你們怎麼了？)
(We, the Hanaoka brothers
are forced to leave this world)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(The savages are massacring the Japanese )
(bringing forth a situation out of control)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(Now we are driven to bay by the savages )
(and have no other choices )
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(It is 9 o'clock on the morning
of October 27th, 1930)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(The savages have already
occupied most of this region)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(The commissioner and all his subordinates )
(have been killed in the school)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
Warriors of The Rainbow II : Rainbow Bridge
Make a phone call!
打電話…
The Wushe savages
are massacring the Japanese
霧社發生暴動了…
Make a phone call! -What happened?
打電話…
怎麼了？
Make a phone call!
快點打電話…
Hurry! -How did it come to this?
怎麼會搞成這樣…
Hurry up and call! -What happened?
打電話…快點打電話…
怎麼了？
What the hell?
-The Wushe savages have revolted
怎麼了…你說清楚…
-到底是…-霧社發生暴動了…
The Wushe savages have revolted
霧社發生暴動了…
Hurry up and call!
快打電話…
Phone!
電話…
Yes?
是…
What?
什麼？
The Wushe savages
are massacring the Japanese?
霧社蕃大出草？
Get everybody here right now
快去把所有人都招集回來…
Massacre...
-Gather all the policemen right away!
-大出草…
-讓開！所有警察集合！
The Wushe savages are hunting heads!
-All the policemen gather up!
-霧社蕃出草了！
-警察回去集合了！
All the Japanese in the mountains
have been killed
山上的日本人都被殺光光了…
And all the police stations
have been burned down
駐在所也被燒光光了…
Only one of the Japanese survived
日本人只剩一個跑出來而已…
Go back home! Come on! Hurry up!
你先回家去…快回去…快
The Wushe savages are coming down
to kill more people
霧社蕃現在要下山來殺人…
They're coming to kill us
殺我們了…
Come on, everyone, hide!
大家趕快躲起來…
Don't get caught -You bastard!
-不要被抓到了…
-混蛋！
What are you talking about?
你再亂講試看看…
The Japanese knew already
日本人已經知道了！
The savages are likely
to charge all the way into Puli
現在蕃人很有可能攻進埔里
We're afraid even the plainsmen
might seize the opportunity to join in the revolt
我們擔心連平地人也乘機聯合造反
This is an emergency
情況緊急…
All county governments please send in
their armies and police forces
希望各州廳調派軍警
to lay siege to Wushe from Hualien and Tunghih
由花蓮、東勢一起圍攻霧社…
And I want to know if the Governor-general
can dispatch the troops
還有台北及台南方面的軍隊
from Taipei and Tainan right away
請總督府馬上調派支援
The Japanese this way, to the sugar refinery
日本人往這邊…往糖廠去…
Come on! The family members
of the Japanese to the sugar refinery
快！日本人家眷快點！往糖廠…
Come on! Hurry up! Put all the stuff away
快點！快點！把攤子收起來…
This way! Hurry up!
往這邊…你們快一點啊！
The family members of the soldiers
to the feedstock department
軍人眷屬往原料廠
The family members of the police
to the mechanical department
警察眷屬往機械廠
The family members of the officeholders
to sugar extraction department! Come on!
公務眷屬往搾糖廠…快點！
You too. Come on!
你們也是…快點！
Come on!
-Savages will always be savages
-快點！快點！
-蕃就是蕃…
You're nothing but beasts
跟野獸一樣…
I never know what you savages are thinking
永遠不懂你們生蕃在想什麼！
It's time for me to teach you a lesson
該換我來教你知道…
Speak Japanese!
講國語！
No one understands your savage language
講一大堆蕃話誰聽的懂啊？
Your tribesmen have revolted
你們部落造反
No more peaceful life for you
你以後也別想好過了…
It's chilly!
很冷…
Come on, Pihu!
快一點呀！畢夫…
Get a larger chunk of wood
放大塊的木頭！
Good morning
早安！
Chief!
大頭目…
It's chilly out here
天氣這麼冷
Why aren't you inside the house by the fire
instead of weaving this bag?
不進屋去烤火
在這編什麼揹袋呢？
It's the first snow of this winter
How could I miss it?
這可是今年的第一場雪哪…
怎麼可以錯過！
The snow has come early this year
今年的雪下早了！
Takun, what are you doing?
達固…
你在幹嘛？
Takun!
達固！
Temu, your son will perform well
on sports day again, won't he?
鐵木…
今年運動會你兒子也會有好成績吧！
Takun, what's going on?
達固…怎麼回事啊？
You've got blood all over your body
怎麼身上都是血啊？
Takun!
達固…
What's wrong with you?
你到底怎麼了？
Chief, today Mouna Rudo from Mehebu Clan
頭目…
今天馬赫坡的莫那魯道…
led the Seediqs from Tgdaya
to offer a blood sacrifice to our ancestors
帶領德克達亞群在霧社血祭祖靈了
They've occupied the whole Wushe region
現在整個霧社已經被他們拿下來了
We Seediqs from Toda should join them as well
我們道澤也一起加入吧！
Let's kill this Japanese man!
殺了這個日本人！
No way!
不行！
Kojima is our friend
He's a good Japanese, not a bad one
小島和我們是朋友！
他是好的日本人，不是壞的日本人…
Go away!
走開！
Temu!
鐵木！
You're the chief of all the Seediqs from Toda
你是道澤總頭目
Why don't you drive the Japanese away
and lead your own people?
你不將日本人趕走
讓自己來治理！
Why should you expect
the good Japanese to rule us?
卻只求讓好的日本人來統治！
He's right! We don't have any Japanese friends
對！
日本人都不是朋友！
Don't come any closer!
不要再過來了！
Kojima, we'll let you answer the phone
小島…
我們讓你去接電話
But do you have the guts to do it?
可是…
你敢接嗎？
Have I been bad to you?
我對你們不好嗎？
Kojima..
小島…
Is this how you repay me?
這就是你們報答我的動作嗎？
I can't fight back if you want me dead
你們要殺我，我無法抵抗
But the Japanese government
will do anything to punish you
但是我們日本政府
一定會因此對你們展開討伐…
We might as well die together
大家同歸於盡吧！
Kojima!
小島…
We have airplanes, but do you?
我們有飛機，你們有嗎？
We have machineguns and cannons,
but do you?
我們有機槍大砲，你們有嗎？
Think about
how Mouna Rudo used to insult you
想想莫那魯道是怎麼羞辱你們的…
Last time when we're out hunting
they threatened to kill you all
上次打獵他們還揚言要殺光你們
Don't you remember?
你們難道忘記了嗎？
Are you willing to die
with them in the battlefield?
現在還要陪他們一起戰死嗎？
Temu Walis,
鐵木瓦力斯？
you won't have the chance to grow up
…我不會讓你長大的！
Hello?
喂…
Take it easy! There's more!
不要搶，還有…別急…
Hurry up!
動作快一點！
Come on!
快一點！
Chief Mouna?
莫那頭目…
Thank you
謝謝你…
謝謝你！
Thank you
謝謝你們！
Thank you. Thank you all
謝謝…真的謝謝你們！
Thank you
謝謝你們！
Thank you -Come on!
-謝謝你們！
-快一點…
Thank you. Thank you all
謝謝！謝謝你們！
Thank you
謝謝你們！
Tado!
達多！
Sapu, where's my father?
薩布，我父親呢？
What's going on? Why did they want us back?
到底在搞什麼？叫我們回來？
Father, why did you give up Hakaw Supeitei?
父親…
為什麼要放棄人止關呢？
So you're back!
回來了啊？
Come on, let's go back to our clan
走！回部落去…
Back to our clan? You're giving up here as well?
回部落？
…連這裡也不要了？
Tado, you can't think like the Japanese
when fighting them
達多…
和日本人打仗不能用日本人的想法…
You have to think like the wind
要用風的想法…
The wind?
風？
The wind is invisible
風是看不見的…
Baso, give up everything, everyone
and come back to the clan with me
巴索…
東西都別拿了，所有人回部落！
Japanese airplanes!
日本飛機…
Over there! -Fire!
-在那邊…
-開槍！
Shoot it! Come on!
開槍打他！快點！
Are you so scared?
這麼害怕嗎？
Are you really so scared?
真的這麼害怕嗎？
I went head hunting for the first time
when I was 15
十五歲那年，我第一次出草…
I was so nervous
that my arms and legs were trembling
我也緊張膽怯，我的手腳發抖…
But my eyes were sharp as arrows
但是…我的眼神如箭！
As soon as I cut the enemy's head off
揮下敵人首級的瞬間…
I forgot what it was like to be scared
我忘記了什麼叫害怕！
because I knew I'd go back to my clan
因為我知道…
to feast and celebrate, being treated as a hero
我將英雄地回到部落接受酒宴歡慶
because I knew that all my people
因為我知道…
male and female, young and old
從今以後部落裡的男女老少…
would respect me for my bravery
都將尊敬我的勇敢！
However, it's different this time
可是…
這次不一樣
We successfully offered a blood sacrifice
to our ancestors today
今天我們雖然成功地血祭了祖靈
and are now qualified
to stride over the rainbow bridge
取得了通過彩虹橋的資格
but what awaits us now is not a festive feast
不過接下來所要面對的…
不是歡慶的酒宴
but to choose how we die
而是選擇死亡的方式！
Run the electricity!
送電！
Before we initiated the revolt
早在起事之前…
you knew it'd turn out like this, didn't you?
你們就知道這種結果了，不是嗎？
My children..
孩子們…
...don't be scared
別急著害怕！
You've been very brave today
你們今天表現得很勇敢
Our ancestors' spirits have seen it all
祖靈們一定也看見了
But the battle to come is the real one
但接下來要面對的才是真正的戰鬥
It's a battle that will terrify the invaders
是要讓異族人嚇破膽的戰鬥…
Someone's here!
有人來了…
Sisin babblers in the forests
are driving off the scavenging crows
森林的祖靈鳥正驅趕著吃腐肉的烏鴉
The rainbow will be more beautiful
in the sunlight after the rain
水氣後的陽光只會讓彩虹更艷麗…
It's a bunch of Hans from Wushe
是從霧社下來的漢人
Lock them all up!
把他們通通關起來…
My children..
孩子啊…
...don't be afraid
別害怕！
Our ancestors' spirits know we're good warriors
guarding our hunting grounds
祖靈會肯定我們是守護獵場的好戰士
The blood stains on your hands can prove it
你們手上的血痕就是印記
Every one of you is a Seediq Bale
你們已經是個賽德克巴萊
Remember, you have to be proud
記住…
要驕傲！
Let's cross the rainbow bridge together
彩虹橋上我們一起過！
Nobody's guarding here
沒人防守啊…
Not a single soul on this path
整條路上上下下全是空的！
How could it be?
怎麼可能？
Advance!
前進…
Wait!
等一下！
Stop! Halt!
停！停下來！
Don't rush uphill
I know these savages all too well
先別上去…
我太了解這些生蕃了…
What a chilly night!
怎麼這麼冷啊…
It's warm here
這個好暖和…
Savages!
有生蕃！
Hold the fire!
停火！
l'm trekking over the high mountains
我走在高山峻嶺上
The creek water is so thick and muddy
溪水是那麼地混濁
l can't help but shed my tears
我忍不住掉下眼淚
l'm walking along a wide road
我沿著寬敞的大路走
He's asleep
他睡著了…
Ichiro?
一郎…
Today is our wedding anniversary
今天是我們的結婚紀念日
You remember, don't you?
…你記得嗎？
We're walking on
with perseverance and determination
我們要坦蕩堅忍地走下去…
We can't fall asleep anymore
已經無法入睡了…
Let's go back to the heavenly home
of our ancestors
快點回祖靈之家呀…
Kojima!
小島！
Long time no see
好久不見了…
Captain!
隊長！
Let me introduce you, Captain
我來向你介紹
This is the chief of Tnbarah Clan, Temu Walis
這位是屯巴拉社頭目鐵木瓦力斯…
Got a good head on his shoulders
聰明的傢伙！
Kojima?
小島…
I heard all your family were killed in the venue?
聽說你的家人都在會場上被殺了？
We will seek revenge
…我們會報復的！
Attack!
突擊！
Officer, nothing here
警部，什麼都沒有啊…
Officer Goto!
後藤警部！
What the hell are these savages up to?
…這些蕃人到底想幹嘛？
The Japanese are coming!
日本人來了…
Look behind you -Yeah
-小心後面…-是！
This clan is over here
這個部落是那邊…
This clan is over there
然後這個部落在那邊…
Behind them is a creek
後面有一條溪流…
Where do the Hans live? -The Hans..
那平常漢人都住在哪裡？
漢人是…
We're under attack! Duck!
有攻擊…趴下！
Hide!
快躲起來！
Awata! Awata!
粟田…粟田…
Contact the Oizumi Squad
and find out where they are now
問一下大泉中隊
看他們到哪裡了…
This is Wushe Substation
這是霧社分室！這是霧社分室！
This is Oizumi Squad
這是大泉中隊！這是大泉中隊！
We're now by Suku Creek
我們現在在斯庫溪…斯庫溪…
We're ambushed by the savages.
We need back up
正遭到蕃人的伏擊…請求支援…
We're stuck in the creek water
現在被困在水中…
Oizumi Squad..
大泉中隊！大泉中隊…
Captain?
大尉…
Assemble a banzai squad for a suicide charge
組織敢死隊，衝上去…
Where is Yamada Police Squad?
山田警察隊呢？
Charge!
衝啊！
Pihu, let's go!
比荷！走了！
Watch out! Dodge!
危險！閃開！
Duck! Seek cover!
閃開！閃開！
The women and children
from Boarung Clan are all here
波阿崙的婦孺都來了…
Come on, let's go!
我們快點了！
Have you packed up enough clothes, Mahung?
馬紅，衣服有多帶嗎？
Yes, I have
有…
Pawan, you kids know how to get there
巴萬
你們幾個孩子知道路
Take the Boarung women and children along
with those of us that are ready
帶外面那些波阿崙的女人孩子
和這邊已經整理好的人先過去…
Baso, I'm no longer a child
巴索，我已經不是孩子了！
Don't let the dogs follow us
We don't have enough food
別讓狗跟著，我們食物不夠…
Mahung, are you ready? Is it heavy?
馬紅…
該帶的都帶了吧？很重嗎？
Mahung, you go ahead with Pawan and others
馬紅
你先和巴萬他們一起過去吧！
I'll wait for Sapu
我等薩布…
Why is everyone in here?
幹嘛都擠在這裡呢？
Mother, don't touch that!
母親，那個不要動…
You're out of your minds!
The men in this house have all gone mad
瘋了！我們家的男人全瘋了…
Go ahead to Paran Clan, Obing
歐嬪…你跟他們去巴蘭社吧！
No!
不要！不要！
Jiro, let me stay with you
二郎…讓我留下來…
Jiro!
二郎…二郎…
Let go of me!
-All pregnant women go to Paran Clan
-不要拉我…
-有身孕的都去巴蘭社吧！
Auntie, I'm the wife of a policeman
姑媽…我是警察的妻子…
but I'm the daughter of the Gungu Chief as well
可是我也是荷戈社頭目的女兒呀…
Auntie, let go of me!
姑媽…
不要拉我…
Give birth to your child in Paran Clan
-不要拉…
-去巴蘭社把孩子生下來…
Jiro! I want to stay with you!
二郎…我要留下來…
I don't want to go there, Auntie!
我不要走…姑媽…
Give birth to your child in Paran Clan
我不要走…我要留下來…
They're all pregnant
她們有身孕
The Japanese won't harm them
日本人不會對她們怎樣的…
Pawan!
巴萬…
巴萬！
What is it?
怎麼啦？
The cavern is right up ahead
You can carry these over by yourselves
岩窟就在前面了
這些東西你們可以搬得過去的…
We have to go now
我們要先走了！
But where to?
…走去哪裡啊？
No, Mother! -Grandmother!
-不要啊…母親…
-祖母…
Mother! -Grandmother!
-母親…
-祖母…
No, Mother! -Grandmother!
-不要啊…母親…
-祖母…
What are you doing?
你在幹什麼？你們在幹什麼啦…
Mother, don't!
母親…不要…
Grandmother! -What are you doing?
-祖母…祖母！
-你們幹什麼啦…
Chief Mouna and others will be here soon
莫那頭目他們等一下就來了…
Grandmother! -Mother!
-祖母…
-母親…
You'll have to fight the Japanese for a long time
你們得跟日本人長期戰鬥…
There's not enough food for all of us
這些存糧不夠那麼多人吃的！
What are you talking about?
你亂講…
Chief Mouna told us we're going to
fight our decisive battle soon
莫那頭目說很快就會決戰的…
Grandmother!
祖母…
Pawan!
巴萬…
I'm so glad that you're a warrior now
guarding our hunting grounds
母親很高興你已是守護獵場的戰士
We'll be waiting for you
at the other end of the rainbow bridge
我們先去彩虹的另一端等著你們！
You'll be meeting us
after you finish your glorious battles
等著你們決戰之後，風光的回家…
Stop following us!
不要跟來…
Fight for your hunting grounds -Mother!
-為你的獵場戰鬥…
-母親…
Grandmother, don't you want me anymore?
祖母…
你怎麼不要我了…
Mother!
母親…
母親…母親…
Pawan, please tell my husband Watan
巴萬，請告訴我的丈夫瓦旦
that I'll have the wine ready for him
at the other end of the rainbow bridge
我在彩虹那端把酒釀好等他過來…
Watan is building up huts in the cavern
You can go tell him yourself
瓦旦就在岩窟搭草寮
你自己去跟他講…
Lubi! Lubi!
露比…露比…
Stop following us! -Mother!
-不要跟來…
-母親…
Don't follow us! -Mother, don't!
-不要跟來…
-母親不要…
Please... -Mother!
-媽媽求你了…
-母親…
Don't cry -Grandmother!
-不要哭…不要哭…
-祖母…
Listen to me..
聽我說…
you're a grownup man now
你現在已經是男人了…
Go on!
去吧…
Grandmother! -To the battlefield!
-祖母…
-去戰鬥吧！
Fight for your hunting grounds!
-Grandmother!
-為你的獵場…用力戰鬥！
-祖母…
To the battlefield!
去戰鬥…
Grandmother!
祖母…
Mother! -Grandmother!
-母親…
-祖母…
Mother!
母親…
Don't go, Mother! -Grandmother!
-不要走呀…母親…
-祖母…
Mother..
母親…
With tears in my eyes
我眼中含淚
l'm walking along a wide road
沿著寬廣的路前進
l beseech you
我懇求你們
Tell me if your hearts are at peace
你們甘心嗎？
Oh, poor innocent children
孩子們是多麼的可憐啊…
What's the matter with you?
你們是怎麼了呢？
We're really exhausted
我們真的非常地疲累…
Hanako?
花子…
You look just as pretty
as you were on our wedding day
你還是跟我們結婚時一樣漂亮…
Good boy! Close your eyes!
乖…眼睛閉起來…
My child, let's go together
孩子…我們一起走吧…
Jiro?
二郎…
Are we the subjects of Japan's Mikado?
我們到底該是日本天皇的子民？
Or the descendants of the Seediq ancestors?
還是賽德克祖靈的子孫？
Do it
…切開吧！
Cut it up and end your conflicts
right here and now
一刀切開你矛盾的肝腸吧…
We don't have to go anywhere once we're dead
哪兒也別去了…
Let's both be free wandering spirits
當個自在的遊魂吧！
Thank you
謝謝…
This way please, General
司令，這邊請…
This is Officer Kabasoa, sir
司令，這位是樺澤警部
He's a local policeman
and he knows the Wushe savages very well
是此地的警察
對霧社地區的蕃情相當熟悉…
Then why are you still alive?
那你為什麼還活著？
He was not there when the incident happened
…他當時不在公學校
General, according to our investigation
司令
根據我們的察訪
there are six clans involved in the revolt
over 300 warriors in all
參與反抗的部落有六個
共有三百多名戰士…
Warriors?
戰士？
You call them 'warriors'
你稱他們為戰士…
Each of these clans took actions separately
他們在凌晨時，各部落單獨行動
at dawn and annihilated
the local police stations
殲滅當地駐在所之後
Then they got together to besiege Wushe
再一起集合圍攻霧社
That's why we don't think it incidental
所以我們判斷這絕不是突發事件
They had been planning it carefully
from the beginning
而是一開始就經過詳細的計劃！
Planning it carefully?
詳細計劃？
Mr. Kabasoa?
樺澤先生…
Don't you think
you're overestimating these savages?
你會不會太高估了這些野蠻人？
General, all our reinforcements
were under fatal attacks yesterday
司令…昨天我們各個支援的部隊
都遭到了嚴重的突擊…
...including here
包括這裡…
This is nothing but animal-like savagery
這只是動物性的野蠻行為…
Once the rain stops,
we'll besiege them immediately
等雨一停，立刻圍攻部落！
Yes, sir!
是！
(Headquarters of Kamada Detachment)
Chief,
頭目…
are we going for the decisive battle tomorrow?
明天要決戰了嗎？
Ah, it hurts!
啊…痛啊…
Chief, the wounds are still fresh
頭目…傷口還沒好哪…
Pawan, you're not a child anymore
巴萬
你已經不是個孩子了！
Chief, can we fight the decisive battle now?
…頭目
我們快點決戰好不好？
What's happening?
發生什麼事…
Give me the gun!
槍給我…
Hurry up!
快…快點…
Let's go!
走！
Hurry up!
快點！
Be careful!
小心！
Go over there! Be careful!
你們過去那邊！
小心一點！
Stop! The savages!
停下來！
有兇蕃！
Stop running!
不要跑！
Over there!
在那邊…
What the hell?
在搞什麼東西啊？
Fire!
開槍！
Retreat! All retreat!
撤退…
全部撤退…
Hurry up and run!
快點…大家快跑…
Seek covers! -Down there!
往下面去…找掩護…
Signalman, call for reinforcements
通訊兵，快通報支援…
Retreat downhill! Hide!
往下撤退…
躲起來…
Out of the way!
讓開！讓開！
Watch out!
後面小心…
Quite slippery here
這邊很滑…
Are you alright?
還好嗎？
Halt, everyone!
前面隊伍停下來…
Jump!
跳下去！
Machine gun!
機關槍…機關槍…
Step back! -Take aim!
-向後退！
-打那邊一點…
You're aiming too high! Hold on to your guns!
你打太高了！槍拿穩…
Come on, fire it,
Sapu! What are you waiting for?
快打呀薩布！等什麼？
I can't fire it
打不出去呀…
Move over! I'll do it!
讓開我來！
Come on! Hurry up!
快跑…快一點…
What the hell? Fell asleep or something?
搞什麼？睡著了啊？
Over there! Come on!
那邊…快點…
He's gone!
跑掉了…
If I aim at the rock deliberately
如果我故意打在石頭上
will the bullet bounce off
and hit the officer over there?
子彈會反彈到後面那個軍官嗎？
Why don't you give it a try?
你試試看…
No, it won't
不行啦…沒有用…
Have you two got too many bullets?
你們兩個子彈太多是不是？
No, but that is a military officer
with a katana sword
不是呀…
那是個軍官哪…帶刀的！
Chief, Tado robbed a couple of machineguns
頭目…
達多搶到了兩挺機槍
Chief Mouna asked us to bring you one and..
莫那頭目叫我們送一挺來給你們…
還有…
here's the ammunition and..
這是彈藥…還有…
and this bag of sweet potatoes
還有這些地瓜…
Kids nowadays are so weak
現在的孩子怎麼這麼沒用啊？
Look how they pant with so little running
才跑沒多遠就喘成這樣！
Do you know how to use it?
這東西你會弄嗎？
I don't think this machinegun works
這機槍好像打不出去…
Why did you give me one that doesn't work?
拿個打不出去的機槍給我幹嘛？
That damned Mouna!
莫那這傢伙…
Chief Dahdo..
塔道頭目
My Paran relatives told me..
我聽到我巴蘭社的親戚說…
that your entire family committed suicide
…你整個頭目家族全都自盡了…
Chief Dahdo, a bigger and more powerful army
is coming our way
塔道頭目…
更大更多的軍隊往這裡圍過來了…
They have lots of cannons
還有好多的大砲！
Pawan, when I was young
巴萬…
我年輕時的威風…
I was no less strong or brave
than your Mehebu Chief Mouna Rudo
可不輸給你們馬赫坡的莫那魯道
you understand?
你懂嗎？
Awi, lead the group and retreat to Rkudaya
阿威…
等一下帶大家退到魯庫達亞…
Chief!
頭目…
Chief! Chief!
頭目…頭目…
Retreat! To Rkudaya!
退！退到魯庫達亞…
Give it to me! Let's go!
拿過來…快走…
Retreat to Rkudaya! Our chief's dead!
快退到魯庫達亞…頭目死了…
Come on!
…快點！
Pihu, come on!
比荷…快點！
Retreat to Rkudaya!
退到魯庫達亞…
Come on! To Rkudaya!
快點！往魯庫達亞！
Come on! Let's go!
快點！快點！
Fire!
發射！
Chase them!
追擊！
Come on!
快！
快一點！
Run in separate ways!
Let's meet up in Rkudaya!
分開跑…往魯庫達亞集合…
Hurry up! Come on!
快點…快點…
Awi, come on!
阿威，快！
Here comes the airplane again!
飛機又來了…
Why is Pihu still there?
比荷怎麼還在那邊？
Come on!
快過去…
Hurry up, Pihu!
比荷，快點！
The bridge is collapsing!
橋要斷了…
Come on, the bridge is collapsing!
快一點…橋要倒下來了…
Medic! Medic!
衛生兵！衛生兵！
Hurry up!
走快一點…
No matter which route we took
we were ambushed by them
不管哪個路線都會掉進他們的埋伏
好像他們早就猜到我們的行動一樣
These savages are too good at this
這些兇蕃太厲害了
We should ask for more reinforcements,
otherwise..
我們應該再增兵支援
否則…
With thousands of soldiers
and all kinds of powerful weapons
幾千名火力強大的武裝部隊
and you ended up being toyed with
by 300 savages?
竟被三百個生蕃給耍得團團轉？
Our airplanes have been patrolling
and bombing all this time
我們飛機在天空飛半天、轟半天…
without killing any savage
為何就是打不到人…
And you call yourselves military officers?
你們這些軍官到底是幹什麼吃的？
Those savages played hit and run
這些兇蕃打了就跑…
They're like ghosts
像鬼一樣…
They ran easily
over the ragged mountain paths
在連站都站不穩的山路上…
that we barely walked properly on
跑起來像飛的一樣
We never knew where they came from
or where they disappeared to
不知道從哪裡來也不知道往哪裡去
They were so unpredictable
完全無法預料呀…
For example, a kid named Pawan Nawi..
像一個叫巴萬那威的孩子
We saw him here the day before yesterday
but we found him here yesterday
前天在這個地方看到
昨天又在這裡被發現
Then he was here today
今天又變到這個地方來了
These are three different places
far away from one another
這些地方距離都那麼遠
No one knows how he managed to do so
這孩子是怎麼跑到的？
…真的搞不懂！
Pawan, have you fought any battle?
巴萬，你們打仗了嗎？
Pawan! -Chief Mouna!
-巴萬…
-莫那頭目…
Chief Dahdo Nokan from Gungu Clan
was killed in a battle
荷戈社的塔道諾幹頭目…
戰死了！
Has anyone seen Mouna Rudo yet?
莫那魯道出現了嗎？
Answer me! -No, sir
回答！
沒有…
That old bastard!
這死老烏龜…
He had the guts to revolt
but he dares not confront me personally
有種造反…
卻沒種出來和我決一死戰
What kind of warrior is he?
What kind of chief is he?
算什麼戰士！算什麼頭目！
Be quiet!
安靜！
They've got lines and lines of defense
and endless reinforcement
一道又一道的防線
怎麼切都切不斷的支援線路…
I can't believe those savages
would have battle plans so well-knit
這樣粗魯的野蠻人
竟然有如此綿密的作戰計畫…
Ask the high command to provide us
with gas bombs
向軍司令部申請糜爛性砲彈！
Gas bombs?
糜爛性砲彈？
I wanted you to be civilized
叫你們文明…
but you forced me to be savage
你們卻逼我野蠻！
You're Mouna Rudo
你是莫那魯道…
but I'm Kamada Yahiko
我可是鎌田彌彥！
From now on..
從現在開始
you're part of the Japanese
military and police forces
你們就屬於大日本帝國軍警隊的一員
You'll have to follow our wartime decrees
今後對軍警的戰地勒令要絕對服從
Those of you who fight bravely
will be rewarded accordingly
對於勇武善戰者…
我們會給予獎賞
But those of you
但是…
who fail to take orders from
the Japanese police or run away
如果不遵從日本警察的命令…
will be punished harshly by law
臨陣脫逃者，絕對依法嚴辦！
Do you understand?
明白了沒？
Now I'm announcing
the bounties of head-hunting
我現在宣布獵首獎金…
We'll give every one of you a gun
我們會發給每個人一把槍！
Come and sign for it after this
等一下每個人都過來登記！
A chief.. 150 to 200 dollars
頭目…
一百五十元到兩百元不等…
An able-bodied man, 100
壯丁…一百元！
A woman, 30
婦女…三十元！
A child, 20
小孩…二十元！
And a special bounty for the head of..
…特別獎
...Mouna Rudo!
莫那魯道
Gas bombs?
糜爛性砲彈？
But sir,
報告…
Gas bombs are still being experimented on
這種炸彈還在實驗階段…
We don't know the effects yet
效果如何也還不知道…
Yes, sir
是…
But currently it's not ready for use
…可是目前真的不適合…
Yes, sir
是…
Come on!
快一點…
Watan, you go that way!
瓦旦，你們往那邊…
Sapu!
薩布！
I'm alright. They hit my sweet potatoes
我沒事！地瓜擋著哪…
Don't stop! Run!
不要停下來，快跑…
Shoot! Shoot him!
快開槍…射他！
Come on!
快！
Out of the way!
不要擋路！
Over there!
那邊！在那邊！
A Seediq from Tgdaya! -Where?
-德克達亞人！
-在哪裡？
He's over there!
跑到那邊了…
Kill him!
殺了他！
Burn it down!
燒掉…
Temu!
泰目…
Come on! Run!
快跑…快跑…
Chief Mouna! It's me, Pawan
莫那頭目
我是巴萬啊…
Chief Mouna! It's me, Pawan Nawi
莫那頭目…
是我，巴萬那威啊…
Chief Mouna, we heard what Baso told you
莫那頭目…
我們有聽到巴索和你說的話…
We know that a large number of
Japanese soldiers have gathered in Suku Clan
大批日軍已經由斯庫社集結…
Time for the decisive battle, isn't it?
是決戰的時侯了吧！
Chief Mouna, we have no family now
Why don't you let us fight?
莫那頭目
我們都已經沒有家人了
為什麼你就不讓我們去打仗呢？
Like everyone else, none of us can sleep or eat
我們和大家一樣…
每天吃不飽、睡不飽
and we don't want to be killed by gas bombs
可是我們真的不想被毒炸彈炸死…
Chief Mouna, look at the tattoos on our faces
We're not children anymore
莫那頭目
你看我們臉上的圖騰
我們已經不是孩子了…
Please let us fight the Japanese
like everybody else
你就讓我們和大家一樣
用力和日本人打一仗吧！
Then I can have a good, long rest
我想好好睡個覺…
We're so tired
我們好累…
We're really exhausted
我們真的好累…
My children, do you remember
where our ancestors came from?
孩子們…
還記得我們的祖先從哪來的嗎？
Mt. White Stone.. -I know. Once upon a time...
-Let me tell the story!
白石山…
-我知道…從前…
-我來講…
Quiet!
安靜！
Can't you wait?
急什麼？
A good hunter should learn how to lie in wait!
好獵人要學會安靜等待！
Pawan, you tell the story
巴萬你講…
Once upon a time on Mt. White Stone
there was a big tree called Pusu Qhuni
從前從前在白石山上…
有一棵大樹，名叫波索康夫尼…
The tree trunk was half wood, half stone
他的樹身…
一半是木頭，另一半是岩石…
One day, a boy and a girl were born
from the tree trunk
有一天，他的樹身生下了一男一女
Then the couple gave birth to lots of children
後來這男女又生下了許多的孩子…
and here we are, the Seediq Bale
就是我們…真正的賽德克人…
Let me help you, Awi
阿威，我幫你吧！
It's ready, my brother
兄弟，準備好了…
I'm ready
可以了…
Let go, my brother
放手吧！兄弟…
Pihu Walis..
比荷瓦力斯…
Don't go! -Let go!
-你不要走…
-放手吧！
I'm in great pain
我真的好痛苦…
Don't go
不要走…
I'm not fighting anymore! No more!
我不要打了…
不打了！
No more!
不打了…
You son of a bitch!
混蛋！
What do you mean by not fighting?
-Kojima!
你說不打了是什麼意思？
小島…
What do you mean by that? -Kojima!
-不打了是什麼意思？
-小島…
Pick it up! Pick up your gun!
撿起來…
把槍給我撿起來！
Out of my way! -Temu!
-走開…
-鐵木…
Temu!
鐵木…
We fight to offer blood sacrifice to our ancestors
我們戰鬥…是為了血祭祖靈
not to revenge the death of your family
不是替你死去的家人報復！
Temu, I know what you saw
鐵木…
我知道你看見了什麼…
but Mouna Rudo has spread the word
asking for your head
但莫那魯道已經放話要拿你人頭了…
This is not the time to make trouble
現在不是惹麻煩的時侯…
Father, you told me only the bravest warriors
父親…
你說過，最美麗的獵場…
are qualified to guard
the most beautiful hunting ground
只有最勇敢的戰士才夠資格去守護
So that's why Mouna Rudo's people and we
have to fight one another constantly
那我們和莫那魯道他們…
是不是要不斷地互相戰鬥…
to prove to our ancestors
that we're the bravest warriors?
才能向祖靈證明自己是最勇武的戰士？
So in the eternal hunting ground
at the other end of the rainbow
那在彩虹頂端的美麗獵場裡…
we'll become allies forever
and there would be no more hatred?
大家是不是就成為永遠的戰友…
不會再有仇恨了？
Yeah, I guess so
…應該是吧！
I want to fight them if possible
to prove my bravery
如果可以的話我也想和他們打一仗
來證明我的武勇…
Sleep, my boy
快睡吧！
Is that our man?
那是我們的人嗎？
Get him! He's a savage! Come on!
快點攔下那個蕃人…快點…
Stop!
不要跑！
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
A savage ran over the suspension bridge
into the woods
有個蕃人從吊橋跑進樹林裡了！
From there? -Yes, from there
-從那邊嗎？
-對，那邊！
Gather up!
集合！
Gather up, First Team!
第一部隊集合…
Gather up!
集合…
First Team!
第一部隊！
Stop!
不要跑！
Good
很好…
Come closer..
再過來…再過來一點…
Good
很好…
Stop, you little bastard
停下來…你這個傢伙…
Aoki!
青木…
Okubo! -Aoki!
-大久保…
-青木…
Where are you? -Aoki!
-你們在哪裡？
-青木…
Okubo! -Aoki!
-大久保…
-青木…
Aoki! Okubo!
青木…大久保…
Let's split up and search!
大家散開來找…
Aoki!
青木…
Okubo! Aoki!
大久保…青木…
Stop!
停…
Everybody, stop!
所有人停下來！
These Seediqs from Tgdaya
are driven crazy by hunger
這些德克達亞真的是餓瘋了…
Okubo!
大久保…
Where are you?
你們在哪裡？
Aoki!
青木…
Where are you?
你在哪裡？
Okubo!
大久保…
Someone's there!
那邊有人！
Where? -In that tree!
-在哪裡？
-在那棵樹上！
Get down!
趴下…
Get down! -Hide!
-趴下…
-躲起來！
Machineguns?
機槍？
Get the mortars!
迫擊砲過來！
Signalman! Signalman!
通訊兵…通訊兵…
Here come the savages!
兇蕃打來了…
It's you then
就是你了！
Chief, Baso is hit!
頭目，巴索被打中了！
Baso! Baso!
巴索…巴索…
Baso!
巴索…
We're in the Mehebu Forest
這裡是馬赫坡森林…
Baso! Baso!
巴索…巴索…
Baso, are you alright?
巴索…你怎麼了…
Baso, be still!
巴索…你不要動…
Retreat!
撤退！
Come on, retreat!
快點撤退…
Get out!
出去！
Get out! Hurry!
出去…快出去！
Inside the hut! Come on!
躲進去…快點…
Get in! Come on!
進去…快一點…
Out of here!
出去！
Don't come in! Get out!
不要再進來了…出去…
Come on! Run!
快點！快跑…
Yes, sir
是…
Is it Mehebu Clan?
馬赫坡社嗎？
Yes, sir
是…
Aim all cannons at the Mehebu Forest
砲口全部對準馬赫坡森林…
End this battle before the sun's out
太陽出來之前結束這場戰爭吧！
Tado! Kill me!
達多…
快把我殺了！
Come on!
快！
It hurts so badly!
我好痛…
Out of the way!
讓開！讓開…
Cut my head off! You hear me?
把我的頭砍下來聽不懂啊…
Get off him!
手拿開…
It's beautiful
好漂亮…
So beautiful
好漂亮啊…
Stop firing please
請停止射擊…
They ran away
他們逃掉了…
Fight till you drop! Seediq Bale!
戰死吧！賽德克巴萊…
Fire the cannons! Fire!
開砲！開砲！
We're under attack!
敵人打來了…
You damned Japanese! Get out of our territory!
可惡的日本人…滾開我們的部落…
You bastards! Get out!
混蛋…還不快滾…
That's one favor I did you Mehebus today
helping you drive our the intruders
今天幫你把異族人趕出馬赫坡一次…
Out of my way! Let me kill them!
前面讓開…我來打！
Temu, give me the bullets!
泰牧…把子彈給我！
Come on! Look out!
快點…小心前面！
Climb up there!
爬上去！
Sine! Sine!
西奈…西奈…
Sine!
西奈…
Sine! Sine!
西奈…西奈…
Stop!
站住！
Come back here!
給我站住！
You take care of him!
去照顧他…
Load the guns! Come on!
裝子彈！快！
Pawan?
巴萬…
You Japanese are finished!
日本人你們完蛋了…
Quick! - Catch him!
-快點…
-追過去！
Off with his head!
獵下他的頭！
Stop!
不要跑…
Don't let him slip away!
不要放過他…
Mouna Rudo!
莫那魯道…
Stop running!
大家不要逃了！
Kill until our blood runs out!
殺到血乾吧…
Cut off their heads like true warriors!
像戰士一樣拿下人頭…
The heavenly home of our ancestors,
here we come!
回祖靈之家唷…
I'm a chief, not your little brother
我是頭目…不是你弟弟…
Iyung! Iyung!
伊勇…伊勇…
Don't touch it, lyung
手不要碰…伊勇…
Iyung!
伊勇…
What are you doing? Move!
幹什麼…走開！
Look out! It's falling down!
倒下去了…倒下去了…
Pawan! Get out of there!
巴萬！快出來！
Pawan, get out now!
巴萬…快點出來！
Pawan!
巴萬…
Iyung! Iyung!
伊勇…伊勇…
Are you alright?
你怎麼了？
Pawan, I've got a good gun
巴萬！拿到好槍了…
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Batu! -Dakis!
-巴杜…
-達基司
Move!
走開！
Ubus!
烏布斯…
Come on! The Japanese are out!
快…日本人跑出來了…
Watch out over there!
小心那邊！
There's one behind him!
後面還有一個…
Don't go there!
不要過去！
Stop!
不要跑！
Bomb!
砲彈！
So you're Mouna Rudo
原來你就是莫那魯道…
Now I see you clearly
我看清楚你了…
Tado, how do we dodge those cannons?
達多…
怎樣才能躲過那些大砲？
Chief, let this ghost lead the way
頭目…
讓我這個鬼魂來帶路吧！
Fire!
開砲！
Look!
看！
Cherry blossoms everywhere!
櫻花開滿天了…
(Those who come forward voluntarily
will be spared)
(Come to the shelters to surrender)
l'm crossing the rainbow bridge
我要走去彼岸的那邊了…
l am Mouna Rudo
我是莫那魯道唷！
Look at the road l've trodden
看我腳步所邁開的道路！
No one's ever gonna stop us
誰也無法抵擋我們…
The determined warriors
決死的勇士啊！
We're home with our enemy's heads
看我們今天帶著首級歸來了…
We're true warriors, like budding pine leaves
像松樹嫩芽般真正的勇士啊！
You must be starved
大家都餓了吧…
and you must be exhausted
也都累了吧！
It's time to decide your future
是該決定自己未來的時侯了…
If you want to take your own life, do it
想自盡的就自盡
If you want to turn yourself in, go ahead
想投降的就投降
If you want to keep fighting..
想繼續戰鬥的…
Tado..
達多…
My dear son..
我的兒子啊…
The hero of Mehebu Clan
馬赫坡的勇者！
Lead them to fight
until you use up all your bullets
你帶他們打完最後一顆子彈吧！
Father! -Chief..
父親！
頭目…
Warriors, forgive me
戰士們！
原諒我…
Forgive me
I don't want the Japanese to insult me
in front of my people
我不願讓日本人在族人面前玩弄我
Forgive me
原諒我…
I'll be waiting for you on the mountain peak
我到山的極巔等你們…
Let's cross the rainbow bridge together
to the eternal hunting ground
一起回到彩虹彼端的美麗獵場…
Father?
父親…
Go..Seediq Bale!
去吧！
賽德克巴萊！
Chief Mouna?
莫那頭目…
Bakan,
巴岡…
bring over everyone from the chief's family
把我們家族的人都帶過來…
Iwan, go back and tell our people in the cavern
依婉…
回去告訴岩窟的族人
that those who don't want to surrender
may as well kill themselves
不想投降的就自盡吧！
I want to fight!
我要去戰鬥…
Me too! -It's over!
我也要去…
結束了…
Mouna!
莫那！
Mouna, where's your ancestral spirit?
莫那…你的祖靈在哪裡？
Where is it?
你的祖靈在哪裡…
There could be greater suffering if you survived
我怕你們承擔不住活下來…
Wipe your face clean
…把臉擦乾淨
Thank you, women and children
謝謝你們女人孩子…
for sacrificing yourselves
to complete the men's souls
成就了部落男人的靈魂…
She's awake!
醒來了…
That savage woman is awake!
那個蕃女醒來了…
Officer Kabasoa!
樺澤警部…樺澤警部…
What's going on?
-That savage woman is awake
-怎麼了？
-那個蕃女醒來了…
Is it Mahung? -Yes, sir
-是馬紅嗎？
-是…
Excuse me!
不好意思…
Let me through!
…借過
Mahung! Mahung!
馬紅…馬紅…
Mahung..
馬紅…
I'm Kabasawa. I've been to your house
我是樺澤…
我去過你們家的…
Do you remember me, Mahung?
記得嗎？馬紅…
Why did you save me?
…為什麼要救我？
My husband and children are waiting for me
我的丈夫孩子都在等我啊…
Mahong..
馬紅…
100 dollars
一百塊錢！
Son of a bitch! What are you doing?
混蛋！你們幹什麼？
Don't put it on the desk!
不要放在桌子上！
What are you looking at? Next!
看什麼？下一個…
It's only a child. You can't get 100 for it
這只是孩子，哪值一百塊？
Get it off!
拿走開！
It's Temu Mouna from Truwan Clan
這是塔羅灣的…泰牧摩那…
What child?
Don't you see the tattoos on his face?
什麼孩子，他臉上有圖騰哪！
Put it over there! What a nuisance!
拿到那邊去啦，囉嗦…
It's Tanah Robe, the Boarung chief
這是…波阿崙頭目達那哈羅拜…
One of you from Gungu Clan killed our chief
你們荷戈社殺了我們頭目…
This one is Pawan Nawi from Mehebu Clan
這是馬赫坡的巴萬那威…
Ukan! Tado!
烏干…達多…
Where are you?
你們在哪裡？
Where is that father going?
那個父親要去哪裡哪？
The father carrying a child on his back
那個父親揹著幼小的嬰孩…
is setting out to shoot the two suns in the sky
要去征伐天上的兩顆太陽了！
They go on and on for a long way
他們走了很遠很遠的路
The child grows up
那個嬰孩長大成人了…
The father dies at an old age
那個父親老死了…
The child takes his father's bow and arrows
孩子揹起了父親的弓箭
The child follows his father's footsteps
孩子繼續父親的路…
toward the rising suns
向著日出之處前進
He gets there at last
…終於到達了呀！
The child gets there at last
孩子終於到達了！
The child shoots a sun down with an arrow
孩子張弓射下了一個太陽
The sun loses its rays
太陽的光芒消失了
The dead sun becomes the moon
死去的太陽變成了月亮
He's a sun-shooting hero
他是射日的英雄！
The sun-shooting hero is returning home
射日勇士又啟程歸鄉了！
The sun-shooting hero has come a long,
long way
射日勇士走了很遠很遠的路…
The sun-shooting hero is home at last
射日勇士終於回家了！
But the hero is already gray-headed
勇士回家已經白髮蒼蒼…
l am drunk today
今天的日子我醉了
l saw him on the way
在路上我看到他了…
The boy from the freezing winter
那個來自酷寒嚴冬下的男孩
A fair-skinned boy like a budding pine leaf
如松枝嫩芽般白白的男孩
Let's dance together
一起來跳舞吧…
Let's enjoy ourselves
讓我們盡興歡聚吧！
l'm drunk today
今天的日子我醉了
Young girls, let's dance together
年輕的女孩我們一起跳舞吧…
Surrender? Why should we surrender?
投降？
為什麼要投降呢？
We've had our enemy's sake wine
我們幾個既然喝了敵人的酒
Doesn't that mean conciliation?
不就算和解了嗎？
Why do we have to surrender?
為什麼還需要投降呢？…
Tado... -Say no more!
-達多…
-不要再講了！
Come on, drink with me
來！你也喝…
Mahung, my little sister...
馬紅…
it's much easier for me to die
哥哥要求死很容易
than for you to go on living
你們要活下去卻很難…
But you must endure
你要多忍耐…
and have lots of children
要多生孩子…
Teach them everything
about the pride of our father
要教他們認識我們父親的驕傲…
Let your children have even more children
讓你的孩子們再生孩子…
and more and more..
再生孩子…
Mahung, have lots of children
馬紅…
再生孩子…
Raise them up to be proud Seediqs
and to live on with pride
要每個孩子都成為驕傲的賽德克
挺起胸膛的活著…
Do you understand?
懂嗎？
Father, Baso and I..
…我、巴索、父親
along with all our fallen people
和死去的族人們…
will be watching over you
from the rainbow bridge
都會在彩虹上看著你們…
Look! The sun is so beautiful
…你看
陽光好美啊！
Oh, my wife!
妻子呀！
ls the wine ready now?
你把酒釀好了嗎？…
Here l come, my wife and children
妻兒呀！我來了唷！
On my way to the heavenly home
of our ancestors
在通往祖靈之家的這路上
Wait a little longer for me please
請你們稍等一會兒
l'll be seeing you soon
我很快就趕來和你們會面了！
We're already on our way
我們已經上路了呀…
Oh my wife and children, wait a little longer
妻兒呀！再等一會兒吧…
Wait for us on the way
to the heavenly home of our ancestors
在通往祖靈之家的這路上等我們
Oh my wife and children, wait a little longer
妻兒呀！稍等一會兒…
We're almost there
我們已經來了…我們已經來了…
We're about to cross the road
就快要越過道路…
We'll be seeing you in no time
我們很快就要相會了！
Wait for us on the way
to the heavenly home of our ancestors
在通往祖靈之家的這路上等我們
Oh my wife and children, wait a little longer
妻兒呀！稍等一會兒…
We're almost there
我們已經來了…我們已經來了…
We're about to cross the road
就快要越過道路…
We'll be seeing you in no time
我們很快就要相會了！
(Pihu Sapu was beaten up to death)
(in the detention house after he got caught)
(Tado Mouna and the last surviving warriors
all committed suicide )
(Mouna Rudo disappeared without a trace )
300 warriors against thousands of soldiers
三百名戰士抵抗數千名大軍
Those survived the battle
killed themselves eventually
不戰死便自盡…
Why did I see
in such a remote mountain area in Taiwan
為何我會在這遙遠的台灣山地
the bushido of samurais
that died over a century ago in Japan?
見到我們已經消失百年的武士精神？
Is it because the cherry blossoms here
are far too red?
是這裡的櫻花開得太艷紅了嗎？
No, these flowers have bloomed early this year
不！
今年的花開早了…
It isn't the season of cherry blossoms yet
現在不應該是櫻花的季節…
(After the incident...)
(Kojima Genji instigated the Seediqs
from Toda)
(to revenge the death of their chief
Temu Walis )
(by killing all the remaining
defenseless tribesmen)
(staying in the shelter during the night)
Out of the way!
前面讓開！
(The few surviving tribesmen were forced)
Hurry up!
快一點！
(to relocate to a compound along
Peikang River)
Out of the way!
前面讓開！
(where the Japanese
could monitor them easily )
Out of the way!
(where the Japanese
could monitor them easily )
(They burned down all their remaining houses )
(before they left)
(Four years later...)
(Mouna Rudo's remains were found)
(inside a cavern,
somewhere deep in the mountains )
(Half of his body rotted to skeleton)
(while the other half
was weathered to a mummy )
(In the following year...)
(the Japanese publicly displayed
his remains and weapons )
(in a wooden crate at the exhibition
celebrating the completion)
(of Nenggao City Hall construction project)
Ah, it's for real
啊~真的啊！
(After that,
his remains disappeared once again)
l'll be arriving soon
(After that,
his remains disappeared once again)
我即將要到達…
l'll be arriving soon
到達祖靈之家！
at the heavenly home of our ancestors
Yes, it's for real
真的…是真的！
Reminisce the people from the past
懷念過去的人們啊
Here l am
我來到這裡
(After the second disappearance )
Here l am
(Mouna Rudo's remains
were recovered 39 years later)
l used to guard
these mountains and forests bravely
(Mouna Rudo's remains
were recovered 39 years later)
我曾英勇守護的山林…
l used to guard
these mountains and forests bravely
(in the specimen room
of the College of Medicine )
l used to guard
these mountains and forests bravely
(in National Taiwan University )
These are our mountains
這是我們的山唷…
Escorted by his offspring)
These are our mountains
These are our creeks
(Escorted by his offspring)
這是我們的溪唷…
These are our creeks
(after 43 years, he finally returned
to his hometown Wushe )
We're the true Seediq Bale
(after 43 years, he finally returned
to his hometown Wushe )
我們是真正的賽德克巴萊唷…
We're the true Seediq Bale
(to be buried properly )
We go hunting in the mountains
我們在山裡追獵…
We share food in our clan
我們在部落裡分享
We fetch water from the creeks
我們在溪流裡取水…
l'm willing to give my life for these
願我為此獻出我的生命…
Oh, creek! Be quiet!
溪流啊！不要再吵了…
Sisin babblers are singing
祖靈鳥在唱歌了…
Sing us a beautiful song please
請唱首好聽的歌吧！
Sing for our people
為我們的族人唱…
a song of our ancestral spirit
來自祖靈的歌…
(List of Angel Fund contributors)
l'm willing to give my life too
願我也獻出我的生命…
(List of Angel Fund contributors)
When the lightening rifts the rock
巨石雷光下
a rainbow appears
彩虹出現了…
and a proud man emerges
有一個人走來了…
A proud man emerges
一個驕傲的人走來了…
Who is this man so proud?
是誰如此驕傲啊？
lt's your offspring
是你的子孫啊…
A Seediq Bale
賽德克巴萊！
Once upon a time on Mt. White Stone
there was a big tree called Pusu Qhuni
從前從前在白石山上…
有一棵大樹，名叫波索康夫尼…
The tree trunk was half wood, half stone
他的樹身…
一半是木頭，另一半是岩石…
One day, a boy and a girl were born
from the tree trunk
有一天，他的樹身生下了一男一女
Then the couple gave birth to lots of children
後來這男女又生下了許多的孩子…
and here we are, the Seediq Bale
就是我們…真正的賽德克人…
Behold! The beautiful rainbow over the hilltop
你們看！美麗的彩虹，在山的那一頭！
My wife and children,
have you brewed the wine?
妻兒呀！你們把酒釀好了嗎？
Drink it!
The wine we offer to our ancestors' spirits
喝吧！獻給祖靈的酒！
Behold! What beautiful rainbow!
My ancestors are calling me
你們看！美麗的彩虹
是祖先在召喚我了！
My wife and children! Are you on your way
to meet our ancestors spirits?
妻兒呀！你們在通往祖靈的路上了嗎？
We should get going too
我們也該上路了
Stand still,
our people who keep the bloodline going
必須延續生命的族人呀！挺起胸膛！
We will be proud like a true Seediq
要驕傲得像個真正的賽德克
Our bodiless spirits will be watching over you
from the rainbow bridge
我們死去的靈魂會在彩虹橋上看著你們
Tell every child to live on forever
告訴每個孩子，生生不息！
To live on like a true Seediq
要活得像個真正的賽德克
Our bodiless spirits
will keep you company in the woods
我們死去的靈魂會在山林裏頭陪著你們
Behold! What beautiful rainbow!
My ancestors are calling me
你們看！美麗的彩虹
是祖先在召喚我了！
My wife and children! Are you on your way
to meet our ancestors spirits?
妻兒呀！你們在通往祖靈的路上了嗎？
We should be on our way too
我們也該上路了
Stand still,
our people who keep the bloodline going
必須延續生命的族人呀！挺起胸膛！
We will be proud like a true Seediq
要驕傲得像個真正的賽德克
Our bodiless spirits will be watching over you
from the rainbow bridge
我們死去的靈魂會在彩虹橋上看著你們
Tell every child to live on forever
告訴每個孩子，生生不息！
To live on like a true Seediq
活得像個真正的賽德克
Our bodiless spirits
will keep you company in the woods
我們死去的靈魂會在山林裏頭陪著你們
Look! -Drink! Drink!
-你們看～
-喝吧！喝吧！
What a beautiful sky!
-We should be on our way
-多美麗的天空呀～
-我們該上路了！
Look! -Drink! Drink!
-你們看～
-喝吧！喝吧！
What a beautiful sky!
-We should be on our way
-多美麗的天空呀～
-我們該上路了！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
We see the rainbow
看見彩虹了唷！